Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
Previously on
Strange New Worlds...
All I ever wanted since
I first saw the stars
was to join Starfleet.
I'm an Illyrian. I've
committed a Federation offense.
If you shelter me they
could come after you. too.
I welcome that discussion.
I'm arresting
Commander Una Chin-Riley
for violations of
our anti-genetic
modification directive.
I didn't ask for this job.
- You need a lawyer.
- She won't respond.
She won't take my calls either.
This is not a plum case.
I'm gonna talk to her
myself. face-to-face.
Just hang in there. Number One.
That's an order. Pike out.
She needs a hospital.
That
is out of the question.
- Her leg isn't healing.
- It will.
It's going
to get infected.
If we go into the
hospital. they might see her
fighting infection. They'll
run tests to find out.
- Mom?
- I know. baby.
I know it hurts.
You're gonna be okay.
I promise.
It needs to get set
or it won't heal.
Her system can't handle it.
She is a child.
She needs a doctor.
Look. if we go to the
hospital now. they'll see.
and we'll lose everything.
Her life will be
ruined. all of ours.
We'll figure this
out. She'll be okay.
Una will be okay.
Starfleet would
like to offer a deal.
Plead guilty to knowingly
submitting false information
to Starfleet by
failing to disclose
your genetic
modification status.
and we'll accept
dishonorable dismissal.
No prison time.
Dishonorable dismissal?
No exile. You'll still be
a free Federation citizen.
Starfleet is willing
to seal your records
and look the other way.
They want to cover
their mistake.
They are grateful
for your service.
Una. you don't want
to drag this out.
And you don't want
others to get dragged in.
It's a fair deal.
It's a good deal.
given the evidence.
She's right. We
won't get better.
This charge can carry
two years imprisonment
at the minimum.
Don't you think we should
sidebar this conversation?
That's a good idea.
Take some time.
talk it over with your counsel.
How can he counsel me
when he works for you?
Captain's personal
log. star date 2393.8.
I have traveled to
the Vaultera Nebula
to find legal help
for my first officer.
The atmosphere here is not
suitable for human life.
The locals. however.
have adapted.
Yes. he's still here.
Yes. I told him.
No. he did not.
Okay.
- Counselor Ketoul still can't see you today.
- I can wait.
I told you she's booked.
She has a deposition.
then an arraignment.
I can wait.
I don't think that you can.
Try me.
Fine.
fine. fine. Okay!
Ugh!
You can take off your mask. Mr. Pike.
The air is safe for you now.
I knew you were stubborn.
I just didn't think
you were stupid.
This planet is
inhospitable to all but...
Except to Illyrians.
Genetically engineered
to survive in this...
charming environment.
You would think that would
allow us a measure of privacy.
Should have returned my calls.
And you should learn
to take a hint.
Or do they not teach reading
the room at the Academy?
Been a while since I
was at the Academy.
so I don't recall.
Una needs your help.
Starfleet Command found
out that she's Illyrian.
It was only a matter of
time before she was outed.
Starfleet will never let an
Illyrian serve. Not openly.
But that is not my
problem. Mr. Pike.
Now. I really do
have a busy day.
Neera.
I don't know what
happened between you two.
but she's your friend.
Una Chin-Riley is not my
friend. and neither are you.
- Please leave.
- I know why you feel the way you do about Starfleet.
the Federation. all of us.
I saw some things.
On a research mission to an
abandoned Illyrian colony.
we found out that it
wasn't so... abandoned.
I saw what can
happen to Illyrians
who reverse their
genetic modification
just so the Federation
will accept them.
Old fears can be
hard to let go of.
but we were wrong about
Illyrians. All of us.
I was wrong.
Congratulations. You
discovered empathy.
Let me know when the rest of
your Federation catches up.
They're going to dismiss her.
Everything she's strived
for. her life's work.
her entire career.
Everything that
she's contributed.
Dishonorable dismissal
is getting off easy.
Starfleet race
laws are draconian.
She's lucky she isn't getting
charged with sedition.
Yes. Mr. Pike. I am
familiar with her case.
The proceedings are sealed.
I make it my business
to know what happens
behind closed doors.
Many of my clients'
lives depend on it.
Now. if that will be all.
How's that working out for you?
- The cases against the Federation.
- Excuse me?
See. I do my homework. too.
Ten cases thrown
out or overturned
in two years for
insufficient evidence?
Good cases. too. as
far as I can tell.
Take this case.
If you win. half the
quadrant will know it.
And it'll bring your other
cases more attention.
Maybe the attention
that they deserve.
Are you attempting to
bribe me. Mr. Pike?
I'm trying to convince you.
I'm trying to save
an old friend.
And maybe do some good here.
Are you? Or are you gonna
let whatever happened
between you and Una
get in the way of
your life's work?
Just take a look
at the case file.
You?
I doubt you'd even
break a sweat.
You're a piece of work. Pike.
Yeah.
But you still haven't said no.
Visitor.
Neera!
I had to see it for myself.
I said this would happen.
After 25 years. the
first thing you say to me
is "I told you so"?
I didn't think you'd...
I'm not here for a reunion.
Tell me the story of the story.
Short version. your words.
Until two months ago.
my record with Starfleet
was spotless.
When they didn't know.
they didn't care.
The only thing that's changed
is that they know the truth.
And that you lied about it.
Must be nice.
What's that?
It's just. some Illyrians
have modifications
they can't hide. and
some of us refuse to.
Neera. I should have...
Please proceed. Commander.
So then somebody turned me in.
and now Starfleet is
asking me to hide again.
so that no one has to know
an Illyrian climbed
the ranks of Starfleet.
It'll be like it never happened.
- Like I never happened.
- So?
You had your playtime.
acting like one of them.
Accept your dismissal. take
your licks and go home.
No.
Why not?
Because I shouldn't
have to hide anymore.
None of us should.
I know I should
have done better.
I didn't stand up
when I should have.
I'm standing up now.
I'll tell opposing counsel
their deal is rejected.
Thank you.
Don't. I'm not
doing this for you.
I'm doing this for me.
And for all the Illyrians
who can't or just won't
pretend to not be who
they really are...
so they can run
away to Starfleet.
Una rejected my deal.
Good.
Do you know how hard it was
to get that deal approved?
I called in every favor.
And do you think that was easy?
Because I can tell
you it was not.
Maybe you should have
thought about that
before arresting her.
Don't be
a child. Chris.
I know you think I betrayed you.
Una should be on my bridge
right now doing her job.
not sitting in some jail cell.
I don't write the code.
and my job... our job...
Oh. our job.
Is to uphold it. regardless.
Una broke the law.
And what if the law is wrong?
Chris. I didn't ask to
be put on this case.
If you stop and
look for one second.
you'll see I've done
everything in my power
to help Una.
That plea deal
was her best shot.
And now that she's
turned it down.
my boss. the judge
advocate general.
is looking into the case.
I don't know why. but
whatever the reason.
it won't be good for Una.
She should have taken the deal.
See you in court.
We'll begin
the arraignment
as soon as the
prosecution arrives.
Ah. What's this?
Vice Admiral Pasalk.
I didn't know you
were joining us today.
Admiral. in light
of the defense's
rejection of a plea bargain.
We would like to petition the
court to amend the charges
against Lieutenant
Commander Chin-Riley.
You may proceed. Captain Batel.
For failure to disclose
her genetic modification status.
we are charging Una Chin-Riley
with knowingly submitting
false information to Starfleet
as well as violating
Starfleet code 614 to 617
prohibiting Starfleet
officers from engaging in
permanent bioengineering.
and two counts of sedition.
We're seeking dishonorable
dismissal and 20 years
in a Federation penal colony.
Space.
The final frontier.
These are the voyages of
the starship Enterprise.
Its five-year mission:
to explore strange new worlds..
To seek out new life
and new civilizations.
to boldly go where no
one has gone before.
Twenty years for lying
on an application?
You decided to fight back and
not make this easy for them.
They want to
make an example out of you.
- What do we do?
- We fight.
Who's first on
their witness list?
Admiral Robert April.
April sponsored my
application to the Academy.
I served under him for
years and he promoted me.
- This is good for us. no?
- No.
Pasalk wouldn't bring
a friendly witness
without a strategy.
Put me on the stand.
Let them see that
being an Illyrian
doesn't change who
I am as an officer.
Are you being funny?
You were never funny.
I know it's normally
not a good idea.
but shouldn't they see me. a
successful Starfleet officer?
It's a good story.
Your story doesn't
matter to their case.
You broke the law.
I put you up there.
they'll just use you to
corroborate their facts.
Or worse. to tear you
down. or likely bring down
a bunch of your so-called
friends with you.
Do you care about my story?
I care that my client
not hand the
prosecution the case.
My way this time. Una.
Your way.
The captain suggested you
could set up shop here.
I bet he did.
Well. she's not using it.
I'll need access
to the Starfleet
Uniform Code of Justice.
I assume it's in your database.
Also. Una's service records.
Thank you. Lieutenant
Noonien-Singh.
Is there something else?
I think I might be of some
assistance to the case.
Counselor. are you familiar
with Starfleet v. Wyck?
I am a civil rights lawyer.
Yes. of course.
If I understand the principle
behind the ruling. then...
Starfleet v. Wyck is
used as an example of
"fruit of the poisonous tree."
If evidence is procured
through illegal means.
it's inadmissible in court.
You think some of the
evidence against Una
was illegally obtained?
If it was. could you
get her case thrown out
on a technicality?
If the evidence was rotten.
I might be able to get
her case dismissed.
Lieutenant. is there something
you know that I should know?
Just let me cover
all the bases first.
Well. you know where I'll be.
May I?
Fraternizing with the enemy?
I'll take my chances.
You look awful.
Thanks for that.
Does this have something
to do with the fact that
your name wasn't on the
witness list for the defense?
I know what you're gonna say.
Putting me on the witness
stand is a terrible idea.
But you want to fight
for your friend.
And I can handle it.
I've served with Una longer
than anyone else on this crew.
I'm in the best position
to speak to her character.
When did you two meet?
Uh. I gave a speech
to her Academy class
forever ago.
That must
have been awful for you.
I know how you hate to give
long. inspiring speeches.
I was speaking about a
test mission I'd flown.
Una came up to me afterward
and. uh. pointed out
- a mistake I'd made during reentry.
- Bold.
And annoying.
But she was right.
She had the guts to tell me.
April once told me that
every good captain needs
a first officer who will
tell him when he's wrong.
Yeah. he said that
to me once. too.
And when did you first
learn that she was Illyrian.
Captain Pike?
I ask again. How
long were you aware
that you were harboring
an Illyrian on your ship.
Captain?
I will remind you
you are on the stand.
and under oath you do not have
the option of not answering.
All right. you've
made your point.
I know you want to
help Una. Chris.
but if you take that
stand. this whole case
becomes about you.
You are the captain
of this ship.
You knew Una was an Illyrian.
and you didn't tell Starfleet.
You could be charged
with conspiracy.
and your whole crew
could be at risk.
No inspiring speeches today.
Today. if you want to help Una.
the best thing you can do is
leave the talking to others.
"Mr. Spock.
"I do hope you
understand why I have to
"throw your friend in jail
simply for being who she is."
"Of course. Mr. Pasalk.
"It is only logical.
Shall we play a round of
Kal-toh this weekend?"
"Yes. That would be enjoyable."
You don't see the tension there?
What tension?
They're all. like. buddy-buddy.
Vulcan bros.
Vulcans
may not give much.
but you can read
their body language.
And those two...
hate each other.
Are you messing
with me right now?
I regret that you had to
witness that outburst.
We won't say a word.
- Mm-mmm.
- Thank you. Doctor.
Of all of my father's
former colleagues.
Pasalk truly brings
out the worst in me.
Ensign Uhura.
I need any communications
referencing Commander Chin-Riley
for the last six months.
Okay. I'll collate.
Including all personal
logs. ship-wide.
Sir. with respect.
per Regulation 25. Section B.
all personal logs remain sealed
unless by order of
Starfleet Command.
- Sufficient evidence...
- I know the rules. Ensign.
I'm giving you an order.
You're doing this to help Una.
Right? She's your friend.
your mentor. I understand.
But you are mine.
And giving me an
illegal order will just
get you in trouble
if I follow it.
I don't think the commander
would want that for you.
Neither do I.
We need to find out
who turned her in.
It might well be the
only way to save her.
Then. respectfully.
we're going to have to
find out another way.
- Nyota...
- I'm sorry. No.
This court
is now in session.
Joining me as judges
in this tribunal
are Space Command
Representative Zus Tlaggul and
Starfleet Commander Chiv.
Commander Chin-Riley.
do you consent
to Captain Batel
as the prosecuting officer?
I do.
Let the charges be read.
Lieutenant
commander Una Chin-Riley
has been formally
charged with violating
Starfleet regulation 614-617.
prohibiting permanent
DNA modification.
as well as submitting false
information to Starfleet.
and two counts of sedition.
How do you plead. Commander?
Not guilty.
The Federation's stance
on genetic engineering is clear.
The practice is
dangerous and illegal.
The reasons for this are many.
but the outcome of the
Eugenics Wars on Earth
speaks for itself.
Tens of millions dead.
Pushed to its limits.
genetic engineering is
nothing short of playing God.
By interfering with DNA and
removing genetic outliers.
we endanger the very essence
of natural evolution.
Captain Batel is right.
Permanent genetic modification
is illegal under Federation law.
Slavery was once legal.
Apartheid was legal.
Discrimination against people
for how they worshipped.
how they loved. their gender.
color of their skin...
All legal at one
time or another.
A law does not make
something just.
I'm not saying the
Federation means to do harm.
Their experience with
genetic modification...
The Eugenics Wars...
Was horrific.
The pain that Earth
felt. unimaginable.
The Federation built
a utopia in its wake.
and in an effort to
protect that utopia.
they became blinded by
a centuries-old fear.
so much so that they
have. perhaps unknowingly.
become persecutors.
My client is only here
because of who she is
and because she felt she had
no other choice than
to hide that fact.
Just like the
millions before her
who were forced to hide
how they worshipped.
how they loved. what
they truly looked like.
because it made others
uncomfortable.
Because it made others afraid.
If a law is not just. then I ask
how are we to trust those
who created that law
to serve justice?
The prosecution calls
Admiral Robert April to the stand.
Admiral April. Una Chin-Riley
served under your command
when you were captain of
the USS Enterprise. correct?
Yes.
But before that. you
sponsored her application
- to Starfleet Academy.
- I did.
So would it be fair to say
you have an investment
in Una's career?
It would.
Admiral. I have to ask.
at any point. did Lieutenant
Commander Chin-Riley
disclose to you that she
was genetically modified?
- No.
- If you had known she was genetically modified.
would you have sponsored
her application
to Starfleet Academy?
Una is an extremely
talented officer.
and one of the most gifted
applicants I'd ever met.
That is not the question. sir.
If you had known Una Chin-Riley
was genetically modified.
would you have sponsored
her application
to Starfleet Academy?
You're under oath. sir.
No. I would not.
Thank you. Admiral.
It takes a big man to
admit his mistakes.
I admire that. Admiral.
Just for the record. could
you tell the court why
you would not have sponsored
Commander Chin-Riley's
Starfleet application.
specifically?
Starfleet Regulation
17. Article 12
explicitly prohibits
genetically modified people.
- such as Illyrians. from serving.
- Of course.
You are an honorable.
decorated admiral.
You wouldn't want
to break protocol
for any one
individual applicant.
- Let me stress this is not personal.
- Right.
It's the law.
Admiral April.
can you tell me what
General Order One is?
Objection. Relevance?
I'm curious myself. Tread
carefully. Counselor.
I will. Your Honor. Admiral.
what is General Order One?
No starship may interfere
with the normal development of
- any alien life or society.
- Yes.
A very important law.
So much so that you
now refer to it as
the Prime Directive.
- do you not?
- Yes. that is correct.
In 2246. while in
command of the Enterprise.
you chose to warn the Perricans.
a pre-warp civilization.
about a possibly
apocalyptic meteor shower
about to hit their planet.
Were you then following
General Order One?
- That was different.
- 2248.
You sent your science officer
to the industrial-age planet
Na'rel to solve
the imminent threat
of an extinction-level drought
by sharing Federation
technology.
- Were you in compliance then?
- Objection. Relevance again.
An entire planet
would have died.
And when you landed on the
hostile planet Man-us 2
without your security officer.
you chose to reveal
your starship
to the pre-warp
civilization Ohawk.
- Objection!
- Did you comply then. Admiral?
Counselor.
I will remind you
the witness is
not on trial here.
Admiral. it would seem
that the rules of Starfleet
only apply when a captain
deems that they do.
Is there a question. Counselor?
Yes.
You have shown
that you have been
repeatedly willing to break
the very first
order of Starfleet
and you are hailed as a hero.
You can break the law if
you so choose. So. hiding
behind order and protocol
to explain why you would
not have admitted Una
Chin-Riley to Starfleet
is a sanctimonious
falsehood. is it not?
- Objection!
- Counselor!
You will cease this line
of questioning at once.
My client did not ask to
be genetically modified.
It is an Illyrian
cultural practice
done to children before
they are even born.
It is done for survival.
and yet she has been arrested
because of a violation of a law.
But the admiral has just shown
us that Starfleet regulations
are flimsy and
subjective at best.
Starfleet captains make
judgement calls every day.
Calls that save lives.
Una Chin-Riley's
services to Starfleet
have been commendable. yes.
But the law that she broke
is there to save lives
and prevent genocide.
So. if you ask me. Counselor.
if I would have denied
Commander Chin-Riley's
access to Starfleet
Academy had I known
she was genetically modified.
my answer is still
yes. I would have.
So you admit that the
reason for your decision
is not law. but fear
and racial prejudice.
- Objection!
- Sustained. - Counselor Ketoul.
this is a court martial
for Una Chin-Riley.
not Admiral April.
That you are unable
to defend your client
does not permit you to
attack the Federation
or our officers.
All of the admiral's
testimony will be stricken
from the court record.
Did Una's lawyer just try
and indict Admiral April?
It would appear so.
I guess that's one strategy.
That didn't exactly
make April look good.
But how does any
of this help Una?
Oh. boy.
So. the lawyer was your idea.
She was.
She's one of the best
civil rights litigators
in the galaxy. and Una's friend.
You know. I think highly of Una.
Promoted her faster than any
other officer on my ship.
Recommended her for
the Medal of Gallantry
after the Marcel
disaster in 2248.
Yeah. I know.
It's a shame the rest of the
court didn't get a chance
to hear that today.
What the hell was that?
You're supposed to defend me.
not attack Admiral April.
- not indict the Federation.
- Why not?
Why are you still
trying to protect them?
I thought you said you
were ready for this fight.
Do you know how rare it is
to get a platform like this?
Platform?
Most Illyrians don't
have your privilege.
Has it occurred to you that
your case might bring us
one step closer in
dismantling the law?
Maybe in the future there
can be justice for Illyrians.
I thought you knew that.
All you ever wanted
here was a soapbox.
This isn't about defending me.
This is just a way for you
to broadcast your hatred
of the Federation.
I thought you were here to
help me. but you're not.
As long as you can make
the Federation look bad.
then who the hell cares if I
get left behind in the process?
I think we both know you're not
the one who gets left behind.
Neera...
That's all in the past.
We should talk about it.
Please.
I told you that I would try.
And that's exactly
what I'm doing.
Because at least with me.
what you see is what you get.
Now. if you'll excuse
me. I have work to do.
The defense calls to the stand
three expert
character witnesses.
La'An Noonien-Singh.
security officer for
the USS Enterprise.
I am the chief science officer.
Chief medical officer
of the USS Enterprise.
I graduated top of my class
and have been promoted
each year during my
tenure in Starfleet.
You were also in consideration
- for the Starfleet Medal of Gallantry.
- Yes.
- So you've saved lives?
When did you first
meet Una Chin-Riley?
On my first day as an
ensign on the Enterprise.
She was part of
the rescue mission
that found me after I escaped
from a Gorn breeding planet.
You have a very
unique last name.
- Do you have any relation to Khan Noonien Singh?
- Yes.
Did you ever suspect
Una to be an Illyrian?
No. I did not.
Did you ever get the sense
that Commander Chin-Riley
was hiding something?
Never.
Just that she was
discreet and empathetic
and handled personal
matters with great care.
Yes. I did get the sense that
she was hiding something.
What was she hiding?
An affinity for Gilbert
and Sullivan musicals.
After the defendant rescued
you. did you remain close?
I had no family left.
Una made sure I
was taken care of.
She sponsored my
application to Starfleet.
Would it be fair to say that
you would not have
joined Starfleet
if not for Commander Chin-Riley?
Counselor. I wouldn't be
alive if it weren't for Una.
And the people you
saved during your career.
would they be alive?
No. they would not.
Mr. Spock. if the
defendant broke the law.
would it follow that the
only logical course of action
is for her to be
punished accordingly?
Perhaps. Although I
think it is illogical
for Starfleet to punish itself.
I'm afraid I don't understand.
The loss of Una
would be destructive
to Starfleet as an organization.
She is an extraordinary officer.
Please describe the nature
of your relationship
with the defendant.
She is a mentor.
I have learned a great
deal about leadership
by serving under her.
She puts the lives of her
crew above her own. Always.
She is a friend.
Family. Una is
family.
Thank you. Lieutenant.
Volume 12.9 of the
Starfleet Uniform
Code of Justice.
If you need anything
else. I will...
Lieutenant. there is one
more thing. I was wondering.
did you have any
luck finding out
how the prosecution learned
that Una was Illyrian?
No. not-not so far.
But you have an idea
about it. don't you?
You think it was you.
Yes.
Why is that?
The night I found out
Una was Illyrian. I was...
I was angry.
I recorded a personal log.
And you think that
somebody got ahold
of that personal log.
and that's how Una was exposed.
- Yes.
- Interesting.
May I ask why you were angry?
It can't be because Una
was genetically augmented.
Considering your last
name. I would think
you would understand the nuances
of genetic manipulation
better than most.
Una was my friend.
She lied to me.
It's not that simple. is it?
- No.
- Could it be
that you carry your
family's augmentations.
and you believe
that because of them
you may become dangerous?
Yes. I do.
There is nothing wrong
with you. Lieutenant.
No hidden monster inside.
- You don't know that.
- But I do.
It's how they make us feel.
They look down at
us for so long that
we begin to look
down at ourselves.
Genetics is not destiny.
despite what you may
have been taught.
The fear you have of
yourself. it's not your own.
It was drilled into you.
You're not born a monster.
You were just born with
a capacity for actions.
good or ill.
Just like the rest of us.
In any case...
it takes six months at a minimum
after a request
from a boatload of admirals
to subpoena a personal log.
They haven't had
nearly that long.
I guarantee. you
are not the person
who leaked Una's true
identity to Starfleet.
But if it wasn't my log
that caused this. then
who turned in Una?
You're head of security here.
Una speaks highly of you.
which is not something
she does of many people.
Who do you think did it?
I-I d... I don't know.
Someone who could gain
from exposing the truth.
My thoughts exactly.
Thank you. You've
been very helpful.
Why do I feel like I've
just been hit by a shuttle?
I'll take that as a compliment.
I would like to
call the defendant
Una Chin-Riley to the stand.
How long have you
been in Starfleet?
Twenty-five years.
Would you call this
career your life's goal?
It's all I've ever wanted.
You knew you were Illyrian.
thus genetically modified.
Didn't you think you
might find yourself
in this position one day?
I had been warned. yes.
So why join Starfleet?
Ad astra per aspera.
Could you translate
for the court?
"To the stars through hardship."
It was the Starfleet motto
before the Federation.
I learned it studying
history in school.
Why were you drawn
to that motto?
I knew it meant we
must endure hardship
to get to the stars.
But I like to think
that it also means
that the stars could deliver us
from anything. That
in the mystery an
vastness of space.
we might not just
satisfy our curiosity.
our need for exploration.
but that in it. we
might each also find...
salvation.
Why would you need salvation?
Was your childhood difficult?
Objection. The defendant's
childhood isn't relevant here.
I'm simply
establishing context.
If Una Chin-Riley is to be
tried for being an Illyrian.
then the court must understand
what it means to be an Illyrian.
We'll allow it to
continue. Counselor.
Thank you.
You grew up in a
Federation colony
in the Vaultera Nebula. correct?
Yes. We were given
provisional membership
in the Federation the
year before I was born.
On the condition that
all genetic modification
was to cease. Is that correct?
- Yes.
- But that didn't happen. did it?
It did for some.
But for other
families. like mine.
it was our tradition.
Our heritage.
What was life like
for your family
under the Federation?
We no longer
discussed our customs.
We performed our
rituals only in secret.
Those who could hid
their modifications.
When new children
were born. parents
sought out friendly
doctors to deliver them.
We knew if we were
ever found to be
genetically augmented
we would be arrested.
Did that ever happen
to anyone you knew?
A boy I went to school with.
Ivan Ketoul.
He was my best friend's cousin.
What happened to him?
Some of us have immune
systems that can glow.
Someone must have seen
him. He came home one day
to find the word "augment"
on their door. We had just
learned about
augments in school.
Opinions on them were clear.
Someone must have found out.
Maybe it was just a prank.
Did anyone defend him.
his family?
Some.
But there weren't enough voices.
Ivan and his parents were
arrested in their home.
He was ten years old.
How did this affect
your community?
Some families moved
to other planets
that weren't Federation.
And those of us who stayed.
we were persecuted.
Circumstances became extreme.
The anti-augmentation
laws seemed to give people
freedom to act on
their worst impulses.
First were the insults.
"Augment."
"Moddie."
"Freak."
There were stores that
wouldn't serve you
if they'd heard
you'd been modified.
Even the rumors
could be dangerous.
I remember when
the attacks began.
We feared for our lives.
Go on.
There was a fight
at school one day.
One boy accused another
boy of being an Illyrian.
I tried to stop it.
My leg got broken.
It was such a simple fix.
So easy to treat
with modern medicine.
But my parents wouldn't
take me to a hospital.
They were afraid.
Despite my modifications.
my leg became infected.
If we hadn't found
and Illyrian doctor
willing to see me in
the middle of the night.
I would have died.
I'm so sorry.
Was this normal for
such a common thing to
become life-threatening?
It was for kids like me. yes.
Civil unrest became so great
the local government decided
to divide us into two cities:
Illyrian and non-Illyrian.
Thank you.
My family. we went to
the non-Illyrian city.
You see. some of us could pass.
We could blend in.
so we did.
We left everyone else
behind. Our families.
Our friends.
We left them all.
I regret it to this day.
I'm so sorry.
And yet.
after all of this strife.
you still wanted to be
a Starfleet officer.
Yes.
One last question. Commander.
How did Starfleet find out
that you were Illyrian?
You managed to keep your status
a secret for so many years.
it's surprising
they found out now.
- I don't...
- Who turned you in to Starfleet?
I remind you. you
are under oath.
I caution you against
badgering your own witness.
- Who turned you in?
- Counselor!
I did.
I turned myself in.
Why?
Why would you risk your career.
the life you built?
I was so sick of living a lie.
of pretending to be
someone I wasn't.
I wanted my crew...
I wanted my crew to know
me for who I really was.
I thought maybe if they did.
I would finally be safe.
And Starfleet would finally
understand Illyrian's better.
So. after all of it...
you still wanted
Starfleet to accept you.
Why?
When I was five or six.
I remember a Starfleet
crew visited.
They were all so...
different from one another.
So many crew members
from so many planets.
It was beautiful. I thought
if all those people
from all those worlds
can work together. side by side.
maybe I could. too.
Maybe I could be a part of
something bigger than myself.
Starfleet is not a
perfect organization.
but it strives to be.
And I believe it could be.
You're saying that...
is why you turned yourself in?
Yes.
Because you believe
in Starfleet.
Yes.
Ad astra per aspera.
Thank you. Commander.
No further questions.
That was a very emotional story.
However. emotions
are irrelevant.
Facts are not.
On what date did
Captain Christopher Pike
learn the truth about your
genetically modified status?
Objection.
This trial is about
Una Chin-Riley.
not her captain.
What we have here is
not just one officer's
violation of the law.
This incident is evidence of
breakdown of chain of command
on board the
starship Enterprise.
starting with its captain.
If Captain Pike was aware
of Una Chin-Riley's fraud
prior to her arrest. and
did not notify Starfleet.
then what we have
here is not fraud.
but conspiracy.
Since my co-counsel
neglected to elicit testimony
from the parties involved.
I will ask the
commander directly.
When did Captain Pike
become aware of your status?
I will also remind the commander
that she is under oath.
And I reminder her that
she does not want
to perjure herself
as I ask one more time.
when did Christopher
Pike first learn
that you were an Illyrian?
Stardate 1224.3
Four months.
Well before your arrest.
For four months.
the captain of the Enterprise
engaged in a conspiracy
to conceal the Illyrian
Una Chin-Riley.
I have no further questions.
The defense wants
you to ignore the facts
in favor of emotion.
But the only matter of
import today is the law.
Una Chin-Riley
broke the law and lied about it.
as her own testimony
has proven. Further.
her actions will likely
lead to a court martial of
one of Starfleet's most
decorated officers.
She is clearly
toxic to Starfleet
in both action an inaction.
Therefore. the only
logical response
is to find the defendant
guilty of all charges.
Captain Batel. are
you familiar with
the Starfleet Code 8514?
I am.
Would you mind reading
that code for the court?
"In extraordinary
and extreme circumstances.
"if the following
conditions are met:
any person
fleeing persecution...
We were persecuted.
I remember when
the attacks began.
"or fearing for their
life due to political
"or religious beliefs.
"cultural engagements or
"biological truths may.
seek safety
within Starfleet...
I thought maybe if they did.
I would finally be safe.
We feared for our lives.
"upon revealing
themselves to authorities
"and making a request.
"may be granted asylum.
I turned myself in.
I wanted my crew to know
me for who I really was.
"Starfleet captains
must exercise discretion
"in judgement when
offering asylum.
"Status is confirmed
by a Starfleet tribunal
or designated authority."
Fearing for their life.
One may seek safety
within Starfleet
and request asylum.
Starfleet has a long tradition
of performing rescue missions.
How many distressed peoples
has Starfleet aided?
How many lives saved?
Una Chin-Riley knew this.
She believed in the
best of Starfleet.
and that through it she
could find salvation
from the hardships and
danger of her everyday life.
Danger she faced
just for being born an Illyrian.
Dangers born of prejudice.
spurred on by laws
against people like her.
But through her hardships.
Una saw the stars.
She joined Starfleet
because she believed
it was the only thing
that could save her life.
She fled persecution.
and within Starfleet
she sought safety.
And then. by turning herself in.
Una fulfilled the third
and final requirement
for asylum.
She asked for it
and Captain Pike granted it.
Like all good
Starfleet captains.
including Admiral
April on Perrican.
Na'rel and Man-us 2.
he exercised his judgement
and gave her asylum.
All this tribunal
needs to do now...
is confirm that status
to absolve them both.
Do you know why I love the law?
Because a law is not
a mirror to society.
A law is an ideal.
A beacon to remind us
how to be our better selves.
And you have the
opportunity today
to do just that.
Mr. Pasalk has made
this case about the law.
and I agree. it is.
By his own argument.
we cannot ignore that
Code 8514 is also law.
All I am asking you
to do today
is to be your better selves
and enforce the law
that favors my client
with the same dispassion
as the laws that
would exclude her.
Years ago...
the ideals of Starfleet
called a young girl
from the far side of
the galaxy to service.
Find those ideals
inside yourself.
Grant Una Chin-Riley
the asylum she was
so clearly seeking.
I think we
could all agree
that the issue of
genetic engineering
is a nuanced one.
The laws prohibiting it
exist for very good reasons.
And regulations must persist
so we may not one day
face another crisis
like the Eugenics Wars.
But this court also believes
that these reasons cannot
and do not allow us to treat
every individual
augment. Illyrian.
or other persons with
modified DNA the same.
Lines must be drawn.
but they must also
shift when necessary.
Perhaps someday Starfleet
and the Federation
may change its views. but today
I'm afraid all we
can do is consider
what the defense has asked.
That we judge the defendant's
specific case
and unique circumstances
independently.
And in that.
we grant the defendant's
request for asylum
and find Una Chin-Riley
not guilty of all charges.
First officer on deck.
- You set me up.
- How so?
You figured it all
out. My admission.
What would happen when
you put me on the stand.
- You knew all of it.
- No.
Not all of it.
Thank you for saving my life.
Hey. what are friends for?
Yeah.
I'm sorry we didn't
do more for Illyrians.
This was a technicality.
It's a start.
As you all know. I am not
the biggest fan of Starfleet.
But I am looking
at a starship crew
that proudly serves under
an Illyrian commander.
So. like I said...
it's a start.
Energize.
Hey.
- La'An.
- Welcome home. Chief.
Place wasn't the
same without you.
If you're all here.
who's flying the ship?
Oh. the thing
practically flies itself.
Back to your
stations. all of you.
Good to have you
back. Number One.
Good to be back. Captain.
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm